Thank you very much, Mr. Chairman, and Secretary Connor and General Spellman, it's great to see you both.
Before I ask
questions, I want to just commend the work of the Corps in the Portland District Office in advancing the Portland Metro levy system. It's a 27-mile levy system along the Columbia River. General Spellman, you were the commanding general at Northwestern Division when the project got underway, and it would be great to see the project come full circle by getting into the construction phase, and I look forward to working with you to see that happen.
Thank you. The Coal Rivers Hatchery, named for an individual, not for a river, Coal Rivers Hatchery is on the Rogue River and it plays an absolutely critical role. Colonel Michael Helton, now retired, went down with me and when we came to the recognition of how many different native fish populations and different rivers that it provided,
and also a rainbow trout for various lakes and the the hatcheries in in great trouble because of the clean lack of clean water and disease that could shut down the hatchery and just kind of 30 years of wear and wear and tear so restoring that hatchery to its full functionality is incredibly important and the Army Corps
to do so needs to identify significant capability for this project. Do you commit to working with the Portland District and my staff and with me in identifying as much capability as possible for restoring the Cole River Satchery? Yes, sir. General, thank you very
much.
I want to
turn to tribal housing on the Columbia River. When the dams were built on the Columbia River, the town for Caucasians that was put inundated was rebuilt, but the villages, the native villages, were never rebuilt. And so we've been working intensely to try to create
Well, right that wrong from now three quarters of a century ago, and the Army Corps released last month the implementation plan for the village development plans for the tribes. And what timeline do you expect to reach the
implementation phase of the plan and begin construction on housing? Yes, sir. I would
just start off my response by saying we are in a much better place than we were five,
six years.
ago and we stepped off on this effort where we were trying to combine the tribes into one consolidated village. The direction we're going now are separate sites for each of the tribes. We are in the process now of identifying the needs and the potential locations, which bank, what site, so that we can get on with the village development plan. So we're about six months into the real estate
development.
Going
down what the the options are and then we'll be able to get into more meaningful discussions on the specifics of each one of those each one of those villages so we have the resources we need and We are in a much better place with with the impacted tribes than we've ever been in the past Well,
I really appreciate that that observation and all the easy to develop land has been developed Along both sides the north bank and the south bank of the river, which means it will never be easy to find these sites They'll be expensive, they'll be difficult
to provide
structure, but it's so important that we address this situation that a legacy wrong that we need to right. And by the way, the Confederated Tribes of the Warm Springs Reservation of Oregon and the Confederated Tribes of the Umatilla Indian Reservation have expressed optimism and appreciation for the level of engagement they've had with the Army Corps at this point. So you're all really doing a great job. And
I'm...
I'm very much impressed by what you've done, and I understand you're planning to continue regular engagement with the tribes? Yes,
sir. That's correct.
Yes. Thank you. In particular, the tribes have noted the cores further along on the displacement assessments for the Bonneville and Dalles Dam pools. Will you also work to expedite the displacement assessments for the John Day and McNary pools? Yes, sir. Thank you very much. Thank you.